Mss.Ms.Coll.27
American Philosophical Society
Jack Schultz papers, 1920-1971
Mss.Ms.Coll.27
American Philosophical Society
27.5 Linear feet Ca. 25,000 items
This collection includes correspondence (18.5 boxes), manuscripts (lectures and articles), research grant material, research data, and some personal notes from his graduate school days. There is significant material relating to his participation in professional organizations such as the American Society of Naturalists (President, 1968), Genetics Society of America (President, 1963), National Research Council, and the National Science Foundation.
27.5 linear feet.
Schultz, Jack,1904-1971.
Box 1-55
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Helen Redfield Schultz and accessioned, 12/--/1983 (1984 9ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Geneticist and biochemist Jack Schultz centered his career on the study of the nature and function of the gene, chemical genetics of Drosophila, cytochemical and nutritional techniques, cytochemistry of growth, and the pattern of human chromosomes. Schultz obtained his A.B., A.M., and Ph.D. (1929) from Columbia University, where he was the last graduate student to get his doctorate under T. H. Morgan. He also worked with Morgan at the California Institute of Technology, 1929-1936 and 1941-1942. As a Rockefeller Foundation fellow in 1937-1939, he worked under Torbjörn Caspersson at the Karolinska Institutet in Stockholm, Sweden. The remainder of his career was spent at the Institute for Cancer Research, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, where he was Senior member and head of the Department of Genetics and Cytochemistry, 1943-1957, and Chairman of the Division of Biology, 1957-1969. Much of his tenure at the Institute was spent as an administrator, rather than on original research. He had much success in choosing, encouraging, and stimulating a brilliant research staff. He did not publish prolifically, relying more on lectures and informal discussions.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Jack Schultz was the last graduate student to earn his doctorate under Thomas H. Morgan at Columbia (1929), joining his mentor at the new biology division at the California Institute of Technology (1929-1936, 1940-1942). Although trained as a geneticist, Schultz began combining classical Drosophila genetics with gene chemistry as early as 1930, when American genetics and biochemistry had little common ground. He also appreciated the significance of nucleic acids in heredity at a time when the protein view of the gene was dominant.
These research interests led Schultz in 1936 to a long-term collaboration with the Swedish biochemist Torbjorn Caspersson on studies of nucleic acids in relation to genetics, and to Schultz's move to the Department of Genetics and Cytochemistry at the Institute for Cancer Research in Philadelphia (1943-1969). His research program was therefore an important link between classical and molecular genetics, and between pure and applied research.
Raised in New York's intellectual milieu, Schultz's temperament inclined him toward synthesis of scientific knowledge. His strength lay in organizing research and in identifying original problems and researchers. He did not enjoy writing, and did not publish or correspond prolifically; the Schultz Papers reflects this pattern in his career.
Alexander, Jerome, b. 1876 ( On genes as colloids.) Correspondence (29 items) 1941-1946 English
American Cancer Society ( Includes information on lectures, research data, grants, and the Scientific Review Committee.) Records (3 folders) 1945-1970 English
American Institute for Biological Sciences ( Includes information on lectures, research data, and grants.) Records (2 folders) 1962-1970 English
American Society of Naturalists ( Includes information on conferences and symposia, committee activities, publications, and educational matters.) Records (3 folders) 1963-1971 English
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989 ( Includes correspondence regarding molecular genetics, the history of genetics, biochemistry, drosophila genetics, Columbia University, Thomas H. Morgan, graduate study, and recommendations.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1946-1970 English
Bonner, David Correspondence (4 items) 1948-1962 English
Bonner, James Frederick, 1910-1996 Correspondence (5 items) 1954-1969 English
Caspersson, Torbjorn Oskar, 1910-1997 ( In 1936 Schultz and Swedish biochemist Caspersson began a long-term collaboration on studies of nucleic acids in relation to genetics. The collaboration grew into a life-long friendship, and continued through correspondence, visits, and exchange of research assistants. The folders contain letters, lectures, and reports, describing their collaboration on genetics and nucleic acids. The pre-1950s material is of special significance, documenting Caspersson's frustrations while working against the mainstream of protein research. The files contain interesting information about other institutions of the life sciences, other research programs, and science in Europe during the war. Together, these records comprise an important chapter in the history of biochemistry, biophysics, genetics, and molecular biology.) Correspondence (11 folders) 1937-1970 English
Demerec, M. (Milislav), 1895-1966 ( On drosophila genetics, Cold Spring Harbor, molecular biology.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1929-1966 English
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, California Institute of Technology, population genetics, Columbia University, conferences and symposia, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, and World War II.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1929-1969 English
Ephrussi, Boris, 1901-1971 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, publications, conferences, and cytogenetics.) Correspondence (11 items) 1934-1968 French
Genetics Society of America ( Contains information on publications, referee's reports, notes, lectures, research data, and grants. Includes folders regarding the American Institute of Biological Sciences, committees, membership information, officer files, and miscellaneous materials.) Records (32 folders) 1926-1971 English
Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964 ( Includes correspondence regarding lectures, publications, human genetics, genetics of plants, drosophila genetics, and displaced German scholars.) Correspondence (4 items) 1933-1936, n.d. English
Hollaender, Alexander, 1898-1986 Correspondence (12 items) 1944-1969 English
Lederberg, Joshua Correspondence (4 items) 1958-1967 English
McClintock, Barbara, 1902-1992 Correspondence (3 items) 1942-1951 English
Mazia, Daniel, 1912-1996 ( On nucleic acids.) Correspondence (11 items) 1941-1970 English
Mirsky, Alfred E. ( Primarily correspondence related to the journal The Cell.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1948-1963 English
Monod, Jacques ( Wedding invitations (2 copies).) Correspondence (2 items) 1938 French
Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945 ( Includes correspondence regarding molecular genetics, physiology, drosophila genetics, fellowships, conferences, and lectures.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1929-1943 English
Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, World War II, radiation genetics.) Correspondence (18 items) 1941-1967 English
National Academy of Sciences ( Includes information on lectures, research data, and grants.) Records (24 items) 1963-1970 English
National Institutes of Health ( Includes information on lectures, research data, and grants.) Records (34 items) 1948-1965 English
National Research Council ( Contains information on committee activities, conferences and symposia, lectures, research data, and grants. Includes information from the Committee on Growth and a Fellowship in Biological Sciences.) Records (5 folders) 1927-1970 English
Rockefeller Foundation ( Includes information on lectures, research data, and grants.) Records (5 items) 1934-1950, n.d. English
Sonneborn, Tracy M., 1905-1981 ( Scientific correspondence.) Correspondence (16 items) 1945-1969 English
Stern, Curt, 1902-1981 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, displaced German scholars, International Congress of Genetics, human genetics, radiation genetics.) Correspondence (21 items) 1930-1969 English
Stern, Kurt Guenter ( On physico-chemical genetics.) Correspondence (11 items) 1944-1951 English
Sutton, Eileen ( On nucleic acids and chromosomes.) Correspondence (12 items) 1940-1943 English
Tatum, Edward Lawrie, 1909-1975 Correspondence (12 items) 1945-1969 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
Torbjorn O. Caspersson studied medicine and biophysics at the University of Stockholm in the 1930s, becoming a lecturer in biochemistry at the chemistry division of the Karolinska Institute (1937-1942), and professor of medical cell research and genetics in 1944. That same year a special research institution was created, the Nobel Institute for Medical Cell Research and Genetics, which soon after was supplemented by the Wallenberg Laboratory of Experimental Cell Research; Caspersson was director of both institutions.
Although he worked within a medical institutional context, Caspersson's research program focused on fundamental aspects of cytogenetics, with a special emphasis on precise spectroscopic measurements. In the 1930s and 1940s, long before the race along the path to the double helix had begun, Caspersson promoted the genetic significance of nucleic acids. Combining his knowledge of cell biology and biochemistry with accurate spectroscopic observations of nucleic acids in living cells, Caspersson concluded in the late 1930s that nucleic acids were somehow involved in protein synthesis, an unorthodox view at a time when protein chemistry dominated the chemical approach to heredity.
Some of this important work was done during a two-year collaboration with Jack Schultz in Stockholm. The collaboration with Schultz, which grew into a life-long friendship, continued through correspondence, visits, and exchange of research assistants. After Schultz left abruptly at the outbreak of the war in 1939, Caspersson attempted to join Warren H. Lewis's cytology laboratory at Johns Hopkins as a Rockefeller Fellow.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Society of Human Genetics Records (1 folder) 1948-1963
American Society of Naturalists Records (3 folders) 1963-1971
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (2 folders) 1946-1970
Briggs, Robert W. Correspondence (15 items) 1943-1949
Caspersson, Torbjorn Correspondence (11 folders) 1939-1970
Cooper, Kenneth Willard Correspondence (2 folders) 1949-1968
Darlington, Cyril Dean Correspondence (1 item) 1933
Demerec, Milislav Correspondence (2 folders) 1929-1966
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (3 folders) 1929-1969
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (11 items) 1934-1968
Faberge, Alexander Cyril Correspondence (3 folders) 1945-1970
Genetics Society of America Records (32 folders) 1926-1971
Hadorn, Ernst Correspondence (31 items) 1954-1970
Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson Correspondence (4 items) 1933-1936
Hecht, Selig Correspondence (5 items) 1930-1940
Klein, George Correspondence (3 folders) 1950-1961
Lewis, Edward B. Correspondence (17 items) 1951-1969
Morgan, Thomas Hunt Correspondence (2 folders) 1929-1943
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (18 items) 1941-1967
National Research Council Records (5 folders) 1927-1929, 1933-1970
National Science Foundation Records (9 folders) Circa 1956-1969
Schultz, Jack Manuscripts (7 boxes) 1920-1971
Stadler, Lewis John Correspondence (2 folders) 1941-1951
Stern, Curt Correspondence (21 items) 1930-1969
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry Correspondence (20 items) 1938-1966
Wald, George Correspondence (8 items) 1935-1969
American Society of Naturalists.; Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989; Briggs, R. W., (Robert W.); Caspersson, Torbjörn, (Torbjörn Oskar), 1910-1997; Columbia University.; Cooper, Kenneth Willard; Darlington, C. D., (Cyril Dean), 1903-1981; Demerec, M., (Milislav), 1895-1966; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Ephrussi, Boris, 1901-1979; Fabergé, Alexander C.; Genetics Society of America.; Hadorn, Ernst, 1902-; Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964; Hecht, Selig, 1892-1947; Institute for Cancer Research (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Klein, George, 1925-; Lewis, Edward B., 1920-; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; National Research Council (U.S.). Committee for Research in Problems of Sex.; National Science Foundation, U.S.; Rudkin, George T.; Stadler, L. J., (Lewis John), 1896-1954; Ward, George; Articles.; Biochemical genetics.; Biology.; Cytochemistry.; Cytology.; Drosophila.; Genetics.; Human chromosomes.; Lectures.
- Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide
  - Alexander, Jerome, 1941-1946; Correspondence ( 29 items )
  - American Cancer Society, 1945-1970; Records ( 3 folders )
  - American Institute for Biological Sciences, 1962-1970; Records ( 2 folders )
  - American Society of Human Genetics, 1948-1963; Records ( 1 folder )
    American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Institute of Biological Sciences; American Society of Human Genetics; Conferences and symposia; Crow, James F.; Genetics Society of America; Human Genetics Society of America; Publication
  - American Society of Naturalists, 1963-1971; Records ( 3 folders )
    American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Institute of Biological Sciences; Business; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Educational matters; Honors -- National Medal of Science; Lewontin, Richard Charles; National Science Foundation; Publication -- BioScience; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
  - Beadle, George Wells, 1946-1970; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Bridges, Calvin B.; Carlson, Elof Axel; Columbia University; Committee activities; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Drosophila genetics; Graduate study; History of biology, especially genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Molecular genetics; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Recommendations; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Bonner, David, 1948-1962; Correspondence ( 4 items )
  - Bonner, James Frederick, 1954-1969; Correspondence ( 5 items )
  - Bridges, Calvin Blackman, n.d.; 3.0 Item(s)
    Biographical and personal data -- Bridges, Calvin B.; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Molecular genetics
  - Briggs, Robert W., 1943-1949; Correspondence ( 15 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Medical research; Mouse genetics; Russian politics and science; World War II -- Impact on science
  - Caspersson, Torbjorn, 1939-1970; Correspondence ( 11 folders )
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Karlinska Institutet; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Lectures, public speaking; Molecular genetics; Publication; Travel -- Sweden; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; World War II -- Sweden
  - Cooper, Kenneth Willard, 1949-1968; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Biographical and personal data -- Krivshenko, Jakov D.; Cytogenetics; Demerec, Milislav; Drosophila genetics; Recommendations; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Darlington, Cyril Dean, 1933; Correspondence ( 1 item )
    Biographical and personal data; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Nobel Prize; Cytogenetics; Molecular genetics; Publication
  - Demerec, Milislav, 1929-1966; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Alava, Aloha Margaret Hannah; Bacterial genetics -- Nomenclature; Bridges, Calvin B.; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Drosophila Information Service; Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict; Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson; Invitations; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; National Science Foundation -- Solicitations for support or contribution; Political issues -- Environment; Russian politics and science; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1929-1969; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    American Philosophical Society; Biographical and personal data; Bridges, Calvin B.; California Institute of Technology; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Columbia University; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Dobzhansky, Theodosius. 70th birthday; Demerec, Milislav; Drosophila genetics; Editorial matters; Instituto Agronomico do Norte; Kerkis, Julius J.; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Population genetics; Russian politics and science; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry; Travel -- Brazil; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; World War II -- Impact on science
  - Ephrussi, Boris, 1934-1968; Correspondence ( 11 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Caspersson, Torbjorn; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Publication; Recommendations -- Davidson, R. L.; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Faberge, Alexander Cyril, 1945-1970; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    Drosophila genetics; Embryology, developmental genetics; Fellowships, assistantships; Genetics of plants; Krivshenko, Jakov D.; Laboratory techniques, equipment; National Science Foundation; Oak Ridge National Laboratory; Radiation genetics; Recommendations; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Genetics Society of America, 1926-1971; Records ( 32 folders )
    American Institute of Biological Sciences; Business; Committee activities; Editorial matters; Genetics Society of America; Publication -- Genetics; Referee's report; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Hadorn, Ernst, 1954-1970; Correspondence ( 31 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; National Academy of Sciences; Publication; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry
  - Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson, 1933-1936; Correspondence ( 4 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Displaced German scholars; Drosophila genetics; Genetics of plants; Human genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Publication; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Hecht, Selig, 1930-1940; Correspondence ( 5 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Columbia University; Conferences and symposia; Davenport, Charles Benedict; Drosophila genetics; Human genetics; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Pauling, Linus; Travel -- France
  - Hollaender, Alexander, 1944-1969; Correspondence ( 12 items )
  - Klein, George, 1950-1961; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    Biographical and personal data; Cancer, chemotherapy; Caspersson, Torbjorn; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Molecular genetics; Mouse genetics; Recommendations; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Lederberg, Joshua, 1958-1967; Correspondence ( 4 items )
  - Lewis, Edward B., 1951-1969; Correspondence ( 17 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Radiation genetics
  - Mazia, Daniel, 1941-1970; Correspondence ( 11 items )
  - McClintock, Barbara, 1942-1951; Correspondence ( 3 items )
  - Mirsky, Alfred E., 1948-1963; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
  - Monod, Jacques, 1938; Correspondence ( 2 items )
  - Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1929-1943; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Biographical and personal data; Carnegie Institution of Washington; Caspersson, Torbjorn; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Fellowships, assistantships; Genetics; Graduate study; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Lectures, public speaking; Molecular genetics; Physiology; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Muller, Hermann Joseph, 1941-1967; Correspondence ( 18 items )
    Bridges, Calvin B.; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Drosophila genetics; Genetics Society of America; L'Heritier, Philippe; National Academy of Sciences; Oster, Irwin; Radiation genetics; Stadler, Lewis John; University of Pennsylvania; World War II -- Impact on science
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1963-1970; Records ( 24 items )
  - National Institutes of Health, 1948-1965; Records ( 34 items )
  - National Research Council, 1927-1929, 1933-1970; Records ( 5 folders )
    Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Drosophila genetics; Fellowships, assistantships; Genetics of plants; Invitations; National Research Council; Radiation genetics; Research support
  - National Science Foundation, Circa 1956-1969; Records ( 9 folders )
    Business; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Miller, Dwight D.; National Science Foundation; Research support; Reviews -- Grant proposals; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1934-1950, n.d.; Records ( 5 items )
  - Schultz, Jack, 1920-1971; Manuscripts ( 7 boxes )
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data -- Bridges, Calvin B.; Cancer, chemotherapy; Caspersson, Torbjorn; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Genetics -- Guinea pigs; Hadorn, Ernst; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Molecular genetics; Mouse genetics; Radiation genetics; Reviews; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Sonneborn, Tracy M., 1945-1969; Correspondence ( 16 items )
  - Stadler, Lewis John, 1941-1951; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Biographical and personal data; California Institute of Technology; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Genetics of plants; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Mampell, Klaus; Political issues -- Loyalty oaths; Publication; Radiation genetics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; University of Missouri
  - Stern, Curt, 1930-1969; Correspondence ( 21 items )
    Becker, Hans Joachim; Biographical and personal data; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Displaced German scholars; Drosophila genetics; Editorial matters; Embryology, developmental genetics; Human genetics; International Congress of Genetics; Political issues -- Germany; Publication -- American Naturalist; Radiation genetics; Recommendations -- Kodani, Masuo; Recommendations -- Lewis, Edward B.; Recommendations -- Stern, Curt; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; University of California, Berkeley -- Miller Research Professorship; University of Rochester
  - Stern, Kurt Guenter, 1944-1951; Correspondence ( 11 items )
  - Sturtevant, Alfred Henry, 1938-1966; Correspondence ( 20 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Biographical and personal data -- Bridges, Calvin B.; Bridges, Calvin B.; California Institute of Technology; Caspersson, Torbjorn; Cytogenetics; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Drosophila genetics; Genetics of plants; History of biology, especially genetics; Honors -- Kimber Award; Lectures, public speaking -- Mendelian Society, Sweden; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; National Academy of Sciences; Publication; Requests for aid in finding positions; Solicitations for support or contribution -- Thomas Hunt Morgan memorial; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Stern, Curt
  - Sutton, Eileen, 1940-1943; Correspondence ( 12 items )
  - Tatum, Edward Lawrie, 1945-1969; Correspondence ( 12 items )
  - Wald, George, 1935-1969; Correspondence ( 8 items )
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Physiology; Publication -- American Naturalist; Requests for reprints